Cruiser Houston Collection, 1917-2003
University of Houston Libraries
- MEMORABILIA
  - Ticket for Valdon S. Roberts, Air Transport Command, September 9, 1945. (Box 33, Folder 37)
  - Uniform of David Flynn (Radioman First Class), dress blues, 1945. (Box 52)
    Donor: David Flynn
  - Uniform of Henry Nickel (Chief Boatswain’s Mate), dress blue uniform with hat frame, late 1940s. (Box 53)
  - U.S. Navy Free Mailing Cards, undated. (Box 33, Folder 38)
  - War ration book, 1943. (Box 33, Folder 39)
  - Wooden cross, die, [1942-1945]. (Box 37)
  - World Revival Hymns book, 1939. (Box 33, Folder 40)
- FILM AND VIDEO RECORDINGS
  This series is divided into the following three formats: VHS videotape, ¾” videotape, and film. Within each format, the recordings are arranged alphabetically by title or subject. The film series includes the nitrate original of a 1930 newsreel, which has been transferred to both 35mm film and VHS videotape for preservation.
  Commercially released videotapes, such as motion pictures or documentaries, have been removed from the Cruiser Houston Collection and cataloged for greater access. To located these videos in the UH Libraries Catalog, search the catalog by entering “Cruiser Houston Collection” as the author, and limit the results of the search to the material type “Video.”
  Patrons wishing to view videotapes in our reading room should contact Special Collections in advance so that we may arrange for a video monitor.
  - Asiatic Fleet Reunion, Washington D.C., 1997 (Vhs 56)
  - Battle of Java Sea - Sunda Strait 50th Anniversary, USS McClusky, March 1, 1992. (Vhs 56)
  - City Greets Cruiser, Paramount Sound News, 1930(two copies) (Vhs 56)
  - Dr. Hekking 89. (Vhs 56)
  - Houston Monument, November 11, 1995. (Vhs 56)
  - Houston Survivor interviews, ( USS Houston (CA 30) Foundation presents The galloping ghost of the Java coast, first cut), November 5, 1996. (Vhs 56)
  - Lost Battalion Association Reunion, Fort Worth, 1988; Holland; Doc Hekking, 1988. (Vhs 56)
  - Lost Battalion Memorial Dedication, Punchbowl, 1994. (Vhs 56)
  - Memorial Service Conducted in the Sunda Strait and Java Sea on April 4, 1993 by USS Houston (SSN-713), April 4, 1993. (Vhs 56)
  - Memorial Service Conducted in the Sunda Strait and Java Sea on April 4, 1993 by USS Houston (SSN-713), 1993. (Vhs 56)
  - Memorial Service, Houston, Texas, March 1, 1997. (Vhs 57)
  - Otto Schwarz at Admiral Nimitz Museum Symposium, Clifton Steamboat Museum, March 18, 1995. (Vhs 57)
  - Otto Schwarz at Hillborough High School, 1991. (Vhs 57)
  - Otto Schwarz Oral History Interview, National Prisoner of War Museum, Andersonville National Historic Site, August 1993. (Vhs 57)
  - Otto Schwarz, USS Houston, The POW Experience. (Vhs 57)
  - Otto Schwarz, USS Houston Survivors Association and HISD, January 25, 1994. (Vhs 57)
  - Rogers (PM Interview). (Vhs 57)
  - Spirit of the Railway: POWs on the Death Railway, Thought Films, 1999, PAL VHS. (Vhs 57)
  - USS Fort McHenry, Sunda Strait 1992; USS Houston Memorial, 1992. (Vhs 57)
  - USS Houston – HMAS Perth Memorial Tree Dedication, Arlington National Cemetery, March 5, 1994. (Vhs 57)
  - USS Houston Memorial Reunion, 1999. (Vhs 57)
  - USS Houston Monument Dedication, November 11, 1995. (Vhs 58)
  - USS Houston Survivor - Scarborough High, February 4, 1993. (Vhs 58)
  - USS McCluskey Wreath Laying, March 1, 1992. (Vhs 58)
  - USS Rentz Commissioning, 1984. (Vhs 58)
  - Wreath Laying: Sunda Strait/Memorial Service: San Antonio. (Vhs 58)
  - [George R.] Brown Room dedication, May 15, 1981 (Videotape 59)
  - George [R.] Brown Room interview; George [R.] Brown Room dedication; [USS Houston (CA-30)?] launching; [USS Houston (SSN-713)] launching. (Videotape 59)
  - City Greets Cruiser, Paramount Sound News, 1930 [film transfer master cassette] (Videotape 59)
  - Houston Survivors Dub, PM Magazine, San Diego, undated. (Videotape 59)
  - Launch of the USS Houston,Houston Survivor’s Association, Dub - WFN, undated. (Videotape 60)
  - Opening, Cruiser Houston (Videotape 60)
  - Thai special, PM Magazine, May 10, 1988. (Videotape 60)
  - USS Houston historical footage: President Roosevelt; [USS Houston] CL-30 launch; night battle action; USS Houston [CL-81] launch, [ca. 1930s-1981]. (Videotape 60)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713) launching, Newport News Shipbuilding, March 21, 1981 (two copies) (Videotape 61)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713) launching, Newport News Shipbuilding, Good Morning America, March 1981 (two copies). (Videotape 61)
  - Bill Weissinger interview and dedication, undated (Videotape 61)
  - City Greets Cruiser, Paramount Sound News, 1930 (labeled Official Ceremonies at Houston City Auditorium…), [nitrate original] (Film 62)
  - City Greets Cruiser, Paramount Sound News, 1930 [35mm dupe negative made in 1995] (Film 62)
- AUDIO RECORDINGS
  This series includes cassette tapes and one audio reel, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - George R. Brown Memorial Room, U of H, May 15, 1981 (Box 63)
  - CBS News programs, 1941-1942. (Box 63)
  - Wayne and Sean Ellerbee, tribute to Houston (Box 63)
  - Ex POW Gala Variety Concert, Melbourne Concert Hall, October 4, 1984 (Box 63)
  - Houston Room dedication, USS Texas, April 1960 (Box 63)
  - Charlie Pryor, Frank Gallagher memorial service, August 1983. (Box 63)
  - Otto Schwarz, Barry Farber Show, WOR-NY, November 16, 1976. (Box 63)
  - Otto Schwarz, High Point High School, May 24, 1980. (Box 63)
  - Sunda Strait, October 12, 1981. (Box 63)
  - USS Houston Bell Ceremony, City Hall [audio reel], January 17, 1974 (Box 63)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713) launch, March 21, 1981; Good Morning America, March 24, 1981 (Box 63)
- MAPS AND SHIPS’ PLANS
  - Battle of Sunda Strait maps, undated (photocopies) (Box 33, Folder 41)
  - Hydrographic chart depicting wreath laying, 50th Anniversary of sinking of USS Houston (CA-30). (Box 33, Folder 42)
  - Ship’s plans, Liebenfels (photocopy), with letter, August 16, 1977. (Box 33, Folder 43)
  - Ship’s plans?, USS Houston (AK-1), undated. (Box 54, Folder 17)
  - Ship’s plans, USS Houston (CA-30), by illustrator Robert F. Sumrall, undated (photographic print) (Box 33, Folder 44)
  - Ship’s plans, USS Houston (CA-30), by illustrator Robert F. Sumrall, undated (Box 54, Folder 18)
  - Ship’s plans, USS Houston (CA-30), original blueprint, 1928 (later reproduction) (Ovs OVS)
  - Southeast Asia map depicting USS Houston locations, created for UH Libraries exhibit, 1997 (Box 54, Folder 15)
  - Strategic Map to Follow the Battle of the Pacific and the Orient, Kansas City Star, January 18, 1942. (Box 54, Folder 16)
  - Thailand-Burma Railway Map, 2002. (Box 33, Folder 45)
- MISCELLANEOUS ARTWORKS
  - Cartoon drawing of dairy farm, 1944. (Box 33, Folder 46)
    Donor: Mrs. Philip Bloemsa
  - Commemorative drawings, [1942-1945]. (Box 33, Folder 47)
  - Drawing of USS Houston by Sean Ellerbee, 1999. (Box 55, Folder 18)
    Donor: Sean Ellerbee
  - Drawing of USS Houston by Sean Ellerbee, 1998 (printed digital copy?). (Box 33, Folder 48)
  - Drawing of USS Houston Presidential Cruise, framed, undated. (Box 33, Folder 49)
  - House plans, with log and addresses, [1942-1945]. (Box 33, Folder 50)
  - The Convoy: USS Houston, USS Peary, print of painting, undated. with article. (Box 55, Folder 16)
  - Source photograph for The Convoy painting, undated (photocopy). (Box 33, Folder 51)
  - USS Houston in Action, Battle of Sunda Strait by John Hamilton, photograph of painting (Box 55, Folder 17)
- FRAMED ITEMS
  Framed items include paintings, photographs, and other types of materials. Many of these items are on permanent exhibition in the library. Some framed items have been reframed or rematted for preservation purposes. They are arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  In some instances, donor information on framed items has been difficult to locate. Special Collections welcomes any additional information that will enable us to properly credit the donors of paintings and other framed items.
  - Battle of Sunda Strait by Oliver Houston, oil painting
  - The Battle of Sunda Strait, poem by H.J. Hill, 1973.
  - George R. Brown photograph, 12 ¼ x 15 ¼”
  - Collage including resolution and photographs, 38 ¼ x 34 ½”
  - Collage including When 88 had the helm…, 29 x 15”
  - Collage of Bernrieder letters and article, 32 x 15 ½”
  - Convoy of the Cripples by Raymond A. Massey, lithographic print, 39 ½ x 31 ½”.
    Donor: William Kirkland
  - Flag used by Henry Latrobe Roosevelt, Assistant Secretary of the Navy, 1933-1936, 16 ¾ x 13 ¼”.
    Donor: Harry L. Roosevelt, III
  - Galloping Ghost by Robert Blake, watercolor, 32 ¼ x 18 ½”.
  - HMAS Perth in Action, Battle of Sunda Strait by John Hamilton, print of painting, 27 ½ x 15.
  - HMAS Perth by J.G. McCredie, oil painting with hat band, 17 x 13”
  - Houston, Temporary White House, photograph, 22 x 10”
  - Houston Volunteers, panoramic photograph, 31 ½ x 9 ¼”.
  - Oil painting by J.G. McCredie, 23 ¾ x 20”
  - Postal covers, 25 ¾ x 20”.
    Donor: Bill Thomas
  - Rock from Hellfire Pass, 13 3/8 x 16”
  - Ship's plan, printed drawing, 38 ¼ x 34 ½”
  - USS Houston by Gr. Perales, oil painting, 47 x 26”
  - USS Houston, oil painting, 30 ½ x 22 ½”>
  - USS Houston in Action, Battle of Sunda Strait by John Hamilton, print of painting, 27 ½ x 15”.
  - USS Houston in Ship Channel, contemporary print of photograph, signed by survivors, 27 ¾ x 23 ¾”
  - USS Houston in Ship Channel, contemporary print of photograph, 27 ¾ x 23 ¾”
  - USS Houston in Ship Channel, photograph, 24 ½ x 20 ½”
  - USS Houston photograph with hat band, 22 ½ x 18 ½”.
  - USS Houston (SSN-713), color photograph, 26 ¾ x 21 ¾”.
    Donor: George H. Mensch
  - USS Houston (SSN-713) launch, photograph, March 21, 1981.
  - USS Rentz Plank Owner Certificate, 21 x 17”.
- PLAQUES
  - HMAS Perth shield, 1985. (Box 67)
  - Naval Command of Western Australia shield, undated. (Box 67)
  - Plaque presented by the Navy League of the United States, Houston Council, August 10, 1985 (Box 66)
  - Presentation of painting by HMAS Perth Survivors, June 9, 1976 (Box 66)
  - Presentation [of photograph?] by USS Houston (SSN-713), September 25, 1982 (Box 66)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) memorial plaque by Joseph W. Wolf, July 10, 1988 (Box 67)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) memorial plaque with map of Dutch East Indies by Joseph W. Wolf, July 10, 1988 (Ovs OVS)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) plaque with champagne bottle from launch, 1943. (Box 65)
  - USS Rentz (FFG-46) shield, June 30, 1984 (Box 66)